Guide to the Ronald L. Brown Collection on Early Instruction at the New York University School of Law MC 12
New York University Archives
Ronald L. Brown Collection on Early Instruction at the New York University School of Law
Bulk, 1831-1856
1831-1856, 1977-1984
MC 12
New York University Archives
0.25 linear feet
The collection contains one series comprising 35 folders of historical notes, memoranda, and photocopied transcripts of correspondence relating to the founding of NYU’s law school and its first dean, Benjamin F. Butler. The collection was established by Ronald L. Brown of the NYU Law Library for his own research. The bulk of the collection’s items consist of photocopied transcripts of correspondence between Butler and others, including Martin Van Buren and J.M. Mathews, preceded by editorial commentary from University Archivist Bayrd Still. The collection also includes memoranda from University Archivists Bayrd Still and Thomas Frusciano concerning Brown’s research, a handwritten list of home addresses where Butler resided between 1836 and 1860, an early lecture syllabus, plans for the law school, a copy of Butler’s inaugural address as dean, and several original pages from an 1858 law school bulletin.
Brown, Ronald L.
Biography of Benjamin F. Butler
Benjamin Franklin Butler, born on December 17, 1795, was a lawyer, legislater, and an influential force in the founding of NYU.
Butler studied law in Albany under Martin Van Buren, who became his law partner and lifelong friend. In November 1824, the New York State Assembly recruited Butler to a commission of lawyers tasked with revising and condensing the New York State legal codes. His role in the legal revisions assured his election to the Assembly four years later.
Beginning in 1833, Butler was appointed Attorney General under the second administration of President Andrew Jackson. For much of his five-year term, Butler also served as chief architect for the formation of the law school within the nascent University of the City of New York. At the conclusion of Jackson's presidency, Butler assumed the principal professorship of the new law school, which he held until his resignation in 1856. He remained in public service during his professorship, serving as federal attorney for the Southern District of New York. Among other anti-slavery activities, he joined Salmon P. Chase in writing the platform for the Free Soil Party in 1848.
Butler died on November 8, 1858 while visiting Paris, France.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into one series.
Brown's Research Materials
Provenance
The letters were transcribed by a typist employed by Mr. Ronald L. Brown of the NYU Law Library. The Archives staff do not have the documents from which the typescripts were made, with the exception of the July 8, 1856, letter enclosed in Folder 34, which may be found in the Records of the Office of the Chancellor (RG 3.0.1).
Scope and Contents
The materials in the collection were compiled by Ronald L. Brown of the NYU Law Library, who was conducting research for a book on law instruction during the early history of the university.
The collection chiefly consists of photocopies of typescript correspondence between Benjamin F. Butler, the first law school dean, and other NYU founders and prominent New York legal figures. Correspondents include Martin Van Buren, J.M. Mathews, David Graham, Jr., H.D. Gilpin, Isaac Ferris, Harmanus Bleecker, and Harriet Butler, the wife of the dean. Each letter is preceded by a summary and contextual note from University Archivist Bayrd Still; Folders 7 and 27a also contain photocopies of Butler's original letters.
In addition to correspondence, the collection includes miscellaneous materials relating to the early history of legal instruction at the University of the City of New York (now NYU). Original pages from an 1858 law school bulletin, as well as photocopies of a June 1835 news clipping, drafts of plans for the law school from Butler and J.M. Mathews, an 1838 syllabus, and transcribed notes from early University Council member William C. Noyes illustrate the goals and activities of the founders of the School of Law (Folders 9-10, 21, 33). Folders 2-3 contain University Archivists Bayrd Still and Tom Frusciano's responses to Brown's research questions regarding the educational ideals of the University's founders, financing and tuition; Samuel J. Tilden's lecture attendance; and the length of terms of study. A photocopy of a transcribed certificate of attendance dated January 1839 (Folder 30) attests to this last question; in response to Brown's tuition and personnel change inquiries, Still enclosed photocopies of two letters from Butler dated September 1839 and July 1856 (Folder 3).
The collection reflects Brown's particular interest in Butler as a research subject. Photocopies of a biographical article written by Arthur A. Ekirch, Jr. are located in Folder 1, and Folder 4 contains city directory listings of Butler's home address between 1836 and 1860, copied by hand. A copy of Butler's inaugural address as principal law professor (Folder 22) is also included in the collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for use without restrictions.
Related Materials
Records of the Office of the Chancellor (1827-1890)
Bayrd Still Papers
Bleecker, Harmanus, 1779-1849; Butler, Benjamin F., 1795-1858; Ferris, Isaac, 1798-1873; Martin Van Buren, 1782-1862; Mathews, J.M., (James McFarlane), 1785-1870; New York University. School of Law.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Law |x Study and teaching.; Lectures.; Memorandums.; Speeches.; Syllabi.
- Series I: Brown's Research Materials, Bulk, 1831-1856; 1831-1856, 1977-1984
  - Arthur A. Ekirch, Jr., "Benjamin F. Butler of New York: A Personal Portrait," New York History, LVIII, no. 1, 1977 January (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Memorandum, T. Frusciano to R. Brown: Mar. 26, 1984. Partial list of documents in Archives relating to B.F. Butler and the Law School, 1984 March 26 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Memoranda and Supporting Materials, B. Still to R. Brown: 1839; 1856; Oct. 13, 1981; Mar. 19, 23, 26, 27; Apr. 9, 1984, answering queries concerning B.F. Butler and law instruction in early history of New York University, Bulk, 1981-1984; 1839, 1856, 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Addresses of office and residence in New York of B. F. Butler and Charles Butler, based on city directories, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - References to intention of founders of University with respect to instruction in law, circa 1831, 1835 August 15 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - B. F. Butler to Harriet Butler, June 2, 1832, 1832 June 2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - J.M. Mathews to B. F. Butler, Jan. 31, 1833, 1833 January 31 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - B. F. Butler to J. M. Mathews, May 29, 1835, 1835 May 29 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clipping, "Law Faculty". Unidentified and undated newspaper account referring to June 2, 1835 meeting of council, 1835 June (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - The Printed Plan: Butler to Mathews, 1835: Plan for the Organization of a Law School in the University of the City of New York; 1858 university bulletin, 1835, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Roberts Vaux to B. F. Butler, Oct. 17, 1835, 1835 October 17 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - John Savage to B. F. Butler, Nov. 3, 1835, 1835 November 3 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - J.M. Mathews to B.F. Butler, Feb. 5, 1836, 1836 February 5 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - J.M. Mathews to B.F. Butler, Feb. 6, 1837, 1837 February 6 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - B.F. Butler to Martin Van Buren, Feb. 15, 1837, 1837 February 15 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - David Graham, Jr. to B.F. Butler, Jan. 20, 1838, 1838 January 20 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - David Graham, Jr. to B.F. Butler, Jan. 23, 1838, 1838 January 23 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - David Graham, Jr. to B.F. Butler, Jan. 27, 1838, 1838 January 27 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - J.M. Mathews to B.F. Butler, Feb. 21, 1838, 1838 February 21 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - B.F. Butler to Harriet Butler, Apr. 7, 1838, 1838 April 7 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Syllabus of lectures to be delivered in Law School, Apr. 24 to Aug. 1, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - B.F. Butler: Inaugural Address, Apr. 18, 1838, 1838 April 18 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - H.D. Gilpin to B.F. Butler, May 29, 1838, 1838 May 29 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - H.D. Gilpin to B.F. Butler, July 30, 1838, 1838 July 30 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Joseph Story to B.F. Butler, July 30, 1838, 1838 July 30 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - H.D. Gilpin to B.F. Butler, Sept. 17, 1838, 1838 September 17 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - David Graham, Jr. to B.F. Butler, Oct. 4, 1838, 1848 October 4 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - B.F. Butler to Charles Butler, Oct. 4, 1838, 1838 October 4 (Box 1, Folder 27A)
  - Martin Van Buren to B.F. Butler, Dec. 14, 1838, 1838 December 14 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - H.D. Gilpin to B.F. Butler, Dec. 15, 1838, 1838 December 15 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Certificate of Attendance, Jan. 10, 1839, 1839 January 10 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - B. F. Butler to W.H.A. Butler, April 22, 1839, 1839 April 22 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - B.F. Butler to Harmanus Bleecker, Nov. 20, 1841, 1841 November 20 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - William C. Noyes, observations on instruction in law, December, 1843, 1843 December (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - B.F. Butler to Chancellor Isaac Ferris, July 11, 1856, enclosing letter of July 8, 1856, 1856 July 8-11 (Box 1, Folder 34)